For it is owing to their wonder that men
both now begin and at first began to
philosophize.
So wrote Aristotle in the 4th century
before Christ. That search for knowledge
and meaning goes on. We still ask the
same questions. Who are we? Why are we
here? How should we conduct ourselves?
Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> By philosophy, we're talking about
a study or areas of thought which
include natural science, mathematics,
ethics, morality. It's very broad and
very very general, very fundamental. And
the other point uh I would emphasize is
that philosophers
uh are quite fearless in their pursuit
of rational argument and this is a very
important feature of the ancient Greeks
as well. Uh they follow arguments
wherever they lead and even if they lead
into unwelcome uh areas. Western
philosophy begins with the Greeks but
not in Greece. Thales the earliest of
the known philosophers came from the
seapport of Mitita in Asia Minor. He
claimed that the first principle of all
things was water.
One of his successors, annexes, said
that matter was formed from air by
condensation and rarifaction.
For the Greeks, the soul was the
principle of life. The soul enclosed the
body as air enclosed the world.
Since air is essential to life, it
followed that there was a link between
it and the soul.
Sadly, we have only three fragments of
Annexameese's writing. For most of our
knowledge of the early philosophers, we
are indebted to later scholars.
The earliest philosophy is called
prescratic philosophy. And uh our
knowledge of it is as it said
fragmentaryary literally fragmentaryary
because we don't have complete books or
writings from these people but
quotations of a few sentences
commentaries by other people on their
works.
[music]
Think of Pythagoras and we think of
geometry and hours spent calculating the
area of the square on the hypotenuse.
His father was an engraver of gems and
the young Pythagoras noted the pure
geometric shapes of the cut crystals.
Quartz crystals would give him a perfect
pyramid. Iron pyites is found in cubes
masked together.
The docahedron is found in nature in the
common garnet and the barrel is a
cylindrical hexagon.
It was with these crystalline shapes
that his imagination constructed the
solid bodies of the universe.
>> He combined an interest in mathematics
and science with uh his role as a sort
of leader of a cult. His principal
contribution is that he sees the nature
of reality as mathematical.
Mathematics,
theory of number, the theory of shapes,
arithmetic, geometry are seen by him as
the understanding of everything
including things which seem perhaps
quite unmathematical like music or the
fate of our souls after death. So that
is the essence of the Pythagorean
vision. I think
>> at the heart of Pythagoras philosophy
was the concept of number. He was
fascinated by the mathematical
relationships between the faces,
vertices, and edges of solid figures. A
cube has six square faces, eight
vertices, and 12 edges.
Much of this was influenced by
astrology, which had spread through the
ancient world from Babylon. Even today,
each sign of the zodiac is associated
with a precious stone.
For Pythagoras, mathematics held the key
to understanding the cosmos. As he named
the universe,
he believed the earth was spherical and
revolved around a great central fire
which we cannot see.
Around this revolved the sun, the moon,
the five known planets, and the fixed
stars.
He had long studied music and the
mathematical ratio between the notes of
the harmonic scale. He believed that
each of the nine spheres that rotated
around the central fire produced its own
note. This was the music of the spheres.
>> Pythagoras noticed a mathematical
relationship between the length of a
column of air or a string in a musical
instrument and the pitch that was
produced when that column of air or
string vibrated. In particular, if you
take a string or column of air of half
the length of the original, you'll get
the note that's an octave above the
original note produced. If you take them
in the ratio 2 to three, then you'll get
the fifth of the scale and so on.
>> But the theory that the universe was
controlled by rational numbers came
crashing down with the discovery of
irrational numbers. An irrational number
is uh a number which cannot be expressed
as a ratio between two whole numbers.
Uh an example an example which mattered
very much to the Pythagoreans is the
square root of two that there is such a
number uh as Pyth Pythagoras own
geometrical theories indicated but it
can't be expressed in terms of the whole
numbers.
uh this was therefore a source of
scandal and shock to the Pythagoreans.
It seemed to undermine their program and
so this uh gave rise to the story
probably a story not a true one but a
plausible one that somebody who revealed
that there are irrational numbers uh was
punished by being drowned at sea.
>> Aside from his experiments in music and
geometry, Pythagoras is best known for
his beliefs in the transmigration of
souls.
Pythagoras believed that there was a
scale of reward and punishment for the
soul after death.
He took his ideas from an ancient
religious sect associated with Orpheus.
It was the Orphics who first developed
the concept of the soul and its
relationship to the body.
In his famous Republic, Plato describes
how the soul of Atalanta, famous for her
running prowess, returned to earth in
the body of an athlete, whilst that of
the vile Theocites was trapped in the
body of an ape. After several
reincarnations, the soul of the true
believer could find release from the
wheel of birth and achieve eternal
peace. Some of the earliest philosophers
or earlier philosophers uh like
Pythagoras as we've as we've mentioned
would think of the soul as something
that could travel between different
bodies which lends itself to a
conception of the soul as immaterial
and an immaterial being that can inhabit
one body or another. Whereas other of
the earlier philosophers notably uh
Lucipus and Democrus would have said
that the soul was merely a material
aspect of the body or or actually a
material part of the body made up of
like super fine particles.
[music] Heracitus arrived in Ephesus
early in the fifth century BC. He had
lived as a hermit eating [music] grass
and had contracted dropsy. He tried to
cure himself by being buried up to his
neck in cowdong. Sadly, he died, but the
idea wasn't nearly as stupid as it
sounds.
Heracitus had often observed how the
heat of the sun drew off moisture from
the earth. He reasoned then that the
heat of the cowdong would [music] draw
off the excess fluid from his body.
The early philosophers had thought that
either air or water was the basic
substance from which the universe was
derived. Heracitus believed it was fire.
Fire lives the death of earth and air
lives the death of fire. Water lives the
death of air. Earth that of water.
Heracletus discovered an intriguing
paradox. That one of the great constants
in life was change.
Sometimes it can be sudden and obvious
like an earthquake. Other changes such
as a stone step worn away by constant
[music] use are gradual and unobtrusive.
All change was caused by universal law.
Heracitus held religion and its
attendant mysteries in contempt.
He believed that his disciples should
use reason to work out the meaning of
life.
He rejected Pythagoras idea that people
should steer a middle course between two
extremes.
Heracitis
insight seems to have been in effect
this that opposites are identical that
um change and stability for example are
two sides of the same coin that they
complement each other that uh good and
bad, sweet and bitter. Many such
opposites uh he was able to show by
example um are in fact not as opposed
and contrasted as they seem to be. uh he
says gold is good for men but bad for
asses. Straw is good for asses but bad
for men. The good and the bad therefore
are the same. The same things are good
and bad. Heracitis identified opposites.
Therefore, uh but the main effect of
this uh was to stimulate in later
philosophers uh a sense of the deep need
to distinguish opposites and provide a
really well motivated and well justified
uh grounding for uh the view that good
and bad are not the same. They really
are different from each other.
Unlike Heracitis, Palmenades denied the
concept of change.
He put forward the idea that nothingness
or void could not exist. If there was no
void in which matter originated or to
which it returned, there could be no
change. Palmenades is credited with the
view uh that change is an illusion that
uh reality is a single unchanging thing.
That's that's the way Palminad's view is
is put. Uh and it's it's not it's not
misleading, but it's important to see
that that is presented as a conclusion
of a a very rigorous argument. And
perhaps Palmenades really should be
regarded as the first person to present
a a really strict deductive argument.
And the argument concluded in the claim
that there is one unchanging reality.
But it's how he got there which is
interesting.
>> Zeno was one of Palmenad's pupils.
He believed the world was one and
indivisible.
He was also intrigued by the phenomenon
of motion and produced several paradoxes
which set out to prove the impossibility
of motion. It's natural to suppose that
I could get up out of this chair and
walk across to the other end of the room
say a distance of 10 yards. Zeno however
maintained that in order to complete
this 10 yard walk I have first to walk
five yards I have to get halfway before
I can get the whole way but before I can
get halfway I have to get a quarter of
the way before that I have to get an
eighth of the way now you can see that
this is an infinite series that we're
embarked upon and there is no literally
no first single step no first distance
that I can can cover in order to yet
embark on my walk. So I can't complete
it. I can't even start it. And the
thought that I could walk and move and
that anything could [clears throat]
change is thus revealed uh to be far
more problematical. In fact, a
straightforward illusion. We rely for
our experience and understanding on our
senses.
To many of the early philosophers,
though, the senses were unreliable.
A large object looked minuscule when
viewed from a distance.
a straight orb blade inexplicably bent
when placed in the water. It would be
left to later generations of scientists
to unravel the mysteries of perspective
and refraction.
In Palmenades and Zeno, we see humankind
beginning to describe the world in
abstract rather than concrete ways.
But Palmenad's view of the world was
oversimplistic.
Either it is or it is not.
Later philosophers would recognize that
life is full of paradox and
contradiction.
Sometimes it is and it is not. The
continued effort to solve such paradoxes
is the beginning of knowledge.
[music]
Like the early philosophers, Empeticles
believed the entire universe to be
composed of the four elements. To them,
he added two forces, love and hate.
Love brings all the elements together.
Hate forces them apart.
Empeticles defined life as the fitting
together of the elements by the rivets
of love.
How could nature produce such diversity
from just four elements? Empeticles drew
a parallel with painters mixing colors.
They create from them forms like to all
things, making trees and men and women
and animals and fish nurtured in water.
Like Pythagoras, Empeticles based his
theories of the nature of matter on the
observation of everyday life.
23 centuries before Charles Darwin, he
was already beginning to grasp the
concept of evolution. Impeticles was
another another of these philosophers
whose who was intellectual personality
was very wide ranging. He ranged from
cosmological speculation to uh religious
pronouncement. He he for example
declared himself to be a god as well as
investigating natural phenomena. That's
the kind of intellectual range we don't
find uh nowadays. Impedles remarkably
reasoned that the speed of light in air
was finite. And of course, we now think
that it is indeed finite. But it took
2,000 years for people to do experiments
to determine that the speed of light in
air was finite. Given that the speed of
light is so fast, it's not easy to
notice the time it takes for light to
travel from an object to the eye.
>> Empeticles believed that all matter gave
off emanations through pores on its
surface.
These emanations in turn were consumed
by other matter.
Tradition has it that he died by hurling
himself into the fiery crater of Mount
Etna because he thought himself a god.
This is certainly an exaggeration.
Empericles may not stand in the pantheon
of the gods, but he ranks amongst the
greatest of the philosophers.
Anaxagaras was the first Athenian
philosopher and a contemporary of
Pericles who soon found himself expelled
from the city.
His crime was to teach that the sun and
moon were not gods as worshiped by the
Athenians, but huge lumps of molten
[music] rock.
Like Empedicles, he did not believe in
the void. Matter did not just appear
from nowhere or disappear into nothing.
It changed and grew.
Anexagoras was fascinated with the
problem of growth and how food became
flesh and bones.
The answer, according to Anexagoras, was
that bits of matter were capable of
infinitely dividing themselves without
the particles disappearing.
Each grain of wheat contained what
Annexagoras called seeds of flesh,
blood, bones, and hair.
Digestion separated [music] out these
seeds, adding like to like. Because the
seeds of wheat are on the surface of a
grain of wheat, the other seeds are
invisible to the human eye.
Anexagoras, like others before him,
tried to explain the phenomenon of
movement.
He believed that matter had been set in
motion by a primal power which he called
noose.
>> Noose means mind.
And a Zacharas talked about the mind. He
maintained that in general everything is
mixed with everything. Uh by which he
meant that if you take any kind of
substance gold, water, blood, uh then in
addition to being blood and gold,
whatever it is, it's everything else as
well. Um, in other words, by analysis,
you could reveal that it contains all
sorts of different kinds of things. And
by this uh view, this insight, he he
thought he could explain how one thing
can turn into another. It's not really
turning into another the other thing
because it's the other thing already.
It's already there.
Mind on the other hand, uniquely was
quite different. Mind was not mixed with
anything. Mind comes in pure form. So uh
what anxist seems to be doing is is
introducing a very fundamental
distinction between two kinds of things.
Mind on the one hand everything else he
didn't call it matter. We might call it
matter. Uh on the other hand mind was
pure and and going along with this view
and an exagoras maintained that mind was
the ultimate source of change and
movement. He explained movement by the
operation of mind.
>> [music]
>> Socrates lived frugally, observing the
Athenian craftsman and using them to
illustrate his theories.
The shoemaker had the skill to make
shoes, so the politician should have the
skill to practice justice, truth, and
statecraftraft. Sadly, this was often
not the case.
Socrates concluded that men act
foolishly and wickedly because they
don't know what's best for them, whilst
the good person never knowingly does
wrong.
>> Socrates sought to understand how we
should live. Uh and and and to practice
the development of understanding. Um
that he called the cultivation of the
soul. Sounds that's a rather um mystic
sounding enterprise, the cultivation of
the soul. But really what he seems to
have understood about it is um
developing yourself and and what does
that mean? What is it about what is
yourself? What is the essence of a
person? Well, it's our ability to
reflect on things to think about things
um to to seek the answers to questions
that that fundamentally is what human
life is about.
And and so that's what Socrates tried to
do. And he went around talking to
people, asking questions, engaging in
arguments. That's what human life is.
That's that's the good life.
>> Socrates became a thorn in the flesh of
the establishment, criticizing them for
their amateurism and self-interest like
some Old Testament prophet. There was
certainly something of the monk about
him. He taught that men should avoid the
material pleasures of the world and
think of their souls.
Perhaps it isn't surprising that in 399
BC he was charged with impiiety and
corrupting the youth of Athens and was
sentenced to commit suicide by drinking
hemlock. He remained calm and controlled
to the end.
Either death is annihilation and the
dead have no consciousness of anything
or as we are told it is really a change
a migration of the soul from this place
to another.
Well, Socrates, I think must must be
counted one of the seminal figures in
the history of philosophy. He he
emphasized the importance of values as
as a central element in human
reflection.
Moral theory, ethics has remained at the
heart of philosophy ever since. This is
a very important part of Socrates's
legacy. He insisted on argument on
rigorous argument on as he would call it
dialectic or dialogue.
uh and again philosophers uh in various
ways in various forms but always in one
form or another have held firm to this
project of engaging in argument of
disputing with each other. So that's
very Socratic not taking things on trust
asking questions where there were
questions to be asked not remaining
content with assumptions or with
authority. This is very Socratic in all
of this. Socrates really shows in
exemplary fashion how to be a
philosopher and that probably is his
greatest influence.
[music]
Let no one who is ignorant of geometry
enter here.
This was the sign above the entrance to
Plato's academy.
Of all the earlier philosophers,
Pythagoras is nearest to Plato in
spirit.
He also shared the views of Palloes and
Zeno on the unreliability of the senses.
Plato un unlike Aristotle who does quote
and refer to earlier philosophers. Plato
doesn't as it were start from earlier
philosophers. He just mentions them
incidentally but clearly he was familiar
with them. um particular ones influenced
him in particular ways. Socrates was his
greatest influence. Um Plato associated
with Socrates when Plato was a young
man. He was one of a group of young men
who went around with Socrates and uh
engaged in discussions and disputes with
them to the annoyance of the rest of
Athenian society. So he was very
strongly influenced by by Socrates and
he really sought in his philosophy to
make sense of what he saw to be implicit
in the Socratic profession of
philosophy.
Uh in other ways Plato was perhaps
negatively influenced by the earlier
philosophers. He as turned away from
them sought to correct what he saw to be
was wrong. In
Plato believed that people were too
ready to accept things at their face
value. One cannot say whether a person's
actions are good or bad until one
defines the good. Laws cannot be called
just or unjust until one defines
justice.
This led Plato to formulate a theory of
forms and ideas.
Plato like Pythagoras believed in man's
immortal soul. He set out his theories
of the soul in his book Fedo.
In it he records Socrates last day on
Earth. Socrates is asked how we acquire
knowledge.
Don't you think that the person who is
likely to succeed in this attempt most
perfectly is the one who approaches each
object as far as possible with the
unaded intellect without taking account
of any sense of sight in his thinking or
dragging any other sense into his
reckoning?
Plato held that at birth the soul forgot
its knowledge of such absolutes as the
good and the beautiful.
Education was a means of helping the
soul to remember them.
Plato often crossed swords with the
sophists. They taught a form of moral
relativism. A thing could be either good
or bad depending upon the circumstances.
Plato believed the good was absolute.
He also had revolutionary ideas on
creation. The earth he believed had been
made by the all creator who embodies
both good and reason.
The creator like the forms is
unccreated, unchanging and real.
Plato was also a political philosopher.
His republic explores the structure of
the city state and the citizen's role
within it.
Once again using Socrates as his main
[music] character, Plato expounds his
view of the ideal state. We all of us
want to live a good life. We'd rather
live well than badly. Whatever we mean
by living well. Well, what do we mean?
What is it to live well? What is the
good life? To be sure of living the good
life, you need to know the answer to
that question. You need a certain form
of insight, knowledge, and
understanding. And Plato argues that
only philosophy can deliver that
understanding. So only the philosopher
has the right to be sure that the life
which he's embarking on and is
prescribing for others if he's in
control only that life is the good life
and only the philosopher is justified in
that conviction. So give the
philosophers control and you'll live a
good life.
During Plato's long life, the power of
Athens as a city state began to wne as a
result of the Pelpeneisian War.
Democracy collapsed and power passed
into the hands of a few aristocrats
known as the 30.
Plato left the city and travel to Egypt,
Syracuse and southern Italy. It was
during this later period that he wrote
the laws.
Hence our epidemics of youthful
irreligion as though there were no gods
such as the law enjoys us to believe in.
He acknowledges the influence of
Socrates on his beliefs. But towards the
end of his life, he began to have doubts
about his earlier theories on forms.
Today, Plato's views on the state seemed
too authoritarian, with no opportunity
for social mobility and education
restricted to the selected few. Perhaps
this is time's revenge, for Plato always
considered time to be life's great
enemy.
>> [music]
>> Aristotle joined Plato's academy when he
was 18 and stayed for 20 years.
After the death of Plato, Aristotle left
Athens and in about 343 BC became tutor
to the future Alexander the Great.
What he probably would have learned from
Aristotle is uh a respect for the world
around us for empirical reality.
Aristotle at that period of his life was
very much uh interested in investigating
the natural world the world of biology.
Also Aristotle in his political theory
to by contrast now with Plato uh was
very alert to the differences between
different kinds of constitutional
arrangement between say tyrannies run by
one person democracies where large
numbers of people are in control.
Aristotle emphasized this variety
uh and was prepared to find good things
to be said for different forms of
government and per perhaps that is a
lesson too which Alexander may have
absorbed usefully as he set off to
travel all over the known world.
Later Aristotle returned to Athens and
set up his own school of philosophy the
Lysan.
It was a parapotetic school. Aristotle
would teach his students as they
strolled together through the grove of
the lysum.
Aristotle believed we could find out all
we needed to know about a person or
object by analyzing its 10 categories or
predicates.
The 10 predicates uh is otherwise known
as categories. We're now talking about
Aristotle's theory of categories which
is a very important element of
Aristotle's thought but quite a comp
complex one. I think what Aristotle is
doing is is distinguishing 10 as he
claims it to be uh fundamentally
distinct kinds of general concept. Uh
the word category links in with the word
predicate and predicates are general uh
rather than names of particular
individual things. So we're concerned
with with general concepts and Aristotle
maintains that general concepts come in
10 irreducibly distinct kinds.
Substances for example are fundamentally
different from qualities, places, times
and so on. And uh a lot of Aristotle's
detailed philosophy is is is based upon
that insight and those distinctions uh
which enable him for example to say that
amongst the different kinds of things
which there are substances occupy a
primary and fundamental role. The other
things aren't substances. They're not
and yet they're not nothing at all.
uh so it's it's a complicated quite a
technical theory but has very wide
repercussions over Aristotle's the
theory and in particular you could say
that Aristotle
if he asked the question is being a
thing a single kind of thing a single
kind of thing Aristotle would say no
being is complex and ambiguous and the
the theory of the 10 predicates or
categories provides a leading clue uh to
that the analysis of that complexity
Aristotle believed that humankind grew
in wisdom and knowledge and that this
sprang from an inquiring mind, an
eagerness to know how nature worked.
Like Plato, Aristotle believed in a god.
But Aristotle's god was not a creator
but a prime mover. Aristotle's god is a
god of the philosophers but it's also a
god of religious theory.
uh Aristotle's god is he describes it as
a being whose nature is to think about
his own thinking that sounds a very
abstract and remote specification but
Aristotle has detailed reasons uh for ma
for maintaining that that does express
the true nature of God and there are two
distinct kinds of reason for for it
firstly um he sees God as the ultimate
cause or source of change in the
universe and for technical reasons which
I won't go into uh the only way in which
something could be an ultimate cause of
change is by being purely intelligible
by being an object of thought.
Uh so there's a rather remote technical
and abstract philosophical reason for
specifying the nature of God in this
way. But there's another reason and
that's this uh for Aristotle's thinking
is is the most valuable aspect of human
life. It's it's what achieves for us the
limited perfection which as human beings
we can achieve. God being by definition
perfect will possess possess this
feature in degrees which we can't. So uh
God thinks in ways and with an intensity
and and an endurance which we can't. God
always thinks about the only thing worth
thinking about namely himself. Uh and so
Aristotle has in fact good reason coming
out both out of his theory of change and
out of his theory of value uh for giving
what is at first sight a very abstract
and forbidding specification of the
nature of God as a being which thinks
about his own thought processes.
>> On the more practical level Aristotle
was interested in ethics and politics.
He believed in the concept [music] of
the good which he defined as that at
which all things aim.
The function of the good man could be
equated with an activity of soul which
follows a rational principle and is
carried out in accordance with goodness
or virtue.
So happiness is an activity not a state
or disposition.
In his ethics Aristotle also advocates
the mean the middle course that avoids
extremes.
The man who shuns and fears everything
and can stand up to nothing becomes a
coward. The man who is afraid of nothing
at all but marches [music] up to every
danger is foolhardy.
Humankind was not self-sufficient.
Male and female were united in the
family. Families were integrated in the
community and the community [music] in
the state.
He also accepted slavery though slaves
should be drawn from foreigners and
barbarians.
Like Plato's ideal republic, Aristotles
had its own fixed hierarchy with no room
for social mobility, but it was less
authoritarian.
Aristotle gives a much richer account of
the ideal state or rather this is the
point the ideal states. Uh he finds good
things to say about many different kinds
of constitutional arrangement. Uh and
correspondingly there are many diverse
ways in which things can go wrong as
well. Um Plato's ideal state says it's
where it's a situation where a
philosopher is in control. So clearly in
some sense it's ruled by an individual
or at least by a very small cery.
Aristotle on the other hand recognizes
that ruled by a single individual or a
small group can be well conducted but of
course it can go horribly wrong. A
despotic tyranny is ruled by one person
which is thoroughly perverse or ruled by
a small clique an oligarchy. On the
other hand, Plato opposed democracy
ruled by the many. Aristotle found some
good things to say about democracy
provided it was conducted in the right
way. Uh that he called that good
constitutional government. But equally
it can go wrong. The if if the mass the
masses the many are ignorant and pursue
bad goals uh then we'll get a thoroughly
bad form of democracy. So uh there are
complex arrangements and they can go
well or badly. Um and that's the
contrast between Aristotle who distin
draws distinct dist distinctions um and
Plato who much more goes down a single
track.
>> Aristotle believed that theater played
an important part in the life of the
state. It was a communal act and also a
therapeutic one. Witnessing the
reenactment of tragic events produced a
cathosis or a purifying of the soul.
Going to the theater was considered such
an important civic act that those on low
incomes were paid to go.
>> He was known for centuries as the
philosopher. Uh and even though now we
don't call him that, there is no
philosopher I think anywhere in the
world through all the diverse forms that
philosophy takes who wouldn't
acknowledge Aristotle as probably the
leading figure in his background.
But let me be more specific. Aristotle
historically led particularly uh into
the natural theology of two major
religions, Christianity and Islam. Um of
course there's more to Christianity and
Islam than than Aristotle. There are the
revealed elements in their in their
respective sacred books but both of them
found in Aristotle a massively
sophisticated and complex philosophical
underpinning uh for the revelations in
the sacred texts.
Um and so Aristotle was influential
throughout the learned and civilized
world of the medieval world both in
Western Europe and in the Arab world uh
for very many centuries. Now there was a
downside to this when finally people
came to try to shake off the rather
restrictive uh form of the religious
authority in the renaissance for
example. uh then Aristotle got blamed
for the bad bits of this authoritarian
dogma uh and came to be seen as an enemy
of scientific advance. That was quite of
course quite unfair because it wasn't
Aristotle who was opposing it but the
religion which had been yolked with
Aristotle.
[music]
With the coming of Christianity,
philosophy took second place to
theology. It tended to look backwards to
the golden age of Plato.
Plato in a way was the most important
person for philosophy and theology uh in
the ancient world. He was known as the
philosopher. Um and Christians although
they were initially reluctant to engage
with philosophy found that they had to
partly because they were under
intellectual attack from philosophers
and partly just because they interested
in making converts and apologetics. And
to do that, particularly if you're
interested in converting or conversing
with intelligent people, involves
dealing with philosophy. And Plato, of
course, was the main philosopher in the
period. I think Christians found Plato
quite appealing because a lot of Plato's
thought and the thought of his followers
um has something in common with
Christianity. For example, uh Plato
thinks that the world was created and
that there was a creator God. Obviously
recognizable
um Christian beliefs as well. He
believes that there's an immaterial soul
very sympathetic for Christians. Um some
of his followers particularly Platinus
and Neoplatonists
um think that there is a trinity of
godlike or divine persons or entities.
um the top one being the one from whom
precedes intellect from whom precedes
soul and Christians were quick to spot
that this bears some resemblance to
their doctrine of the trinity. Um so it
may just be that part of the reason why
Plato was so appealing apart from his
overall pervasiveness is that uh
Christians found they can actually learn
something from him. We certainly know
from Augustine that uh part of his
conversion to Christianity and the uh
route that he went through involved
reading the Plleonists and learning from
them and from them seeing how
Christianity was as it were the perfect
form of really a pagan philosophy.
>> Augustine of Hippo lived from 354 to 430
AD and came from a Christian family. He
accepted Plato's ideas on the forms
which he said were thoughts in the mind
of God.
All human knowledge was a product of
illumination by God. Human happiness is
being at one with God.
Augustine believed God existed in
eternity and created the world from
nothing. Creation is an absolute. How
then can there be change? Augustine
thinks that God himself is timeless and
immutable in line with normal
neoplatonic thought. Um, and his view is
that this timeless and immutable God
creates the world of temporal and
changing things. So that there's a a
very strong contrast between the two.
Change itself is explained by Augustine
in a somewhat unexpected way. Augustine
thinks again following certain
neoplatinists particularly Platinus that
as it were intrinsic in things is a kind
of capacity for change such that if you
like earlier stages of the universe um
have the wherewithal to develop into
later stages of the universe. He has a
very evolutionary theory but unlike the
neoplatanist he doesn't think this
evolutionary process is unsupported. He
thinks that God is active right the way
through sustaining this developmental
process and the world of changing
things.
>> He thought that the state existed to
further the well-being of the individual
in a well-ordered environment.
Then in 410 AD, the Visigothth sacked
Rome. Two years later, he began writing
the city of God.
Unlike Plato's Republic or Aristotle's
politics, this is not a treatise on the
ideal earthly city. In Augustine's work,
the city of God is contrasted with the
city of Babylon.
>> [music]
>> It was Albertus who introduced Aquinus
to the works of Aristotle.
Like the Greek philosopher, Aquinus
believed that truth could be arrived at
by logic and reason. Aquinus followed
Aristotle's theories about the movement
of the spheres that bore the heavenly
bodies. But Aquinus [music] believed
that angels were the causes of this
movement. The fundamental feature of
angels for Aquinus is that they lack
matter. The reason for this is that
matter is that principle which allows
something to be destroyed by some
natural agent. [music] And Aquinus
thinks that angels are indestructible by
any agent other than God. The lack of
matter has a rather disconcerting
consequence, which is that um each angel
is a different species. Michael the
Archangel is as different from Gabriel
the Archangel as a dog is from a cat
perhaps. The reason for this is that
Aquinus thinks that material substances
like you and me are distinguished from
each other by effectively being
different lumps of matter.
Angels don't have matter. So they must
be distinguished from each other in some
other way. And the way in which Aquinus
believes they are distinguished is by
being different kinds of thing. But its
lack of matter also means that it can't
exist in the universe in the same way as
material beings do. And Aquinus believes
that for an angel to be present in the
universe is just for an angel to be
causing an effect somewhere in the
universe. And that's all there is to it.
>> Aquinus taught that men as political
animals needed the state to further the
ends of its citizens.
But human law was subordinate to both
natural and divine law.
The church existed to further men's
union with God.
>> Although Aristotle was very useful for
the medieval theologians, there were
certain difficulties that were raised
and that kept on cropping up really
throughout the 13th century.
Fundamentally, Aristotle's worldview is
very naturalistic. There's not really a
place in it for creator god, for
example. Aristotle thinks that the world
is everlasting. It doesn't have a
beginning, and his god is something
rather different from the Christian's
creator.
matters reached something of a crisis in
the 1270s, culminating in 1277 with the
condemnation of a large number of
Arisetilian claims taken from really
Christian writers through the 1260s and
1270s including Thomas Aquinus who was
recently dead by then. The Archbishop of
Paris took exception fundamentally
to
what theologians perceived to be the
necessitarianism
of Arisetilian thought. That is to say
that everything happens as a matter of
necessity including not only uh um the
actions of creatures but also the
creative act of God. And this was felt
to be inconsistent with Christianity in
quite a a big way.
>> [music]
[music]
>> like Aquinus, Scotas set out proofs of
the existence of God. He went to Paris
but was expelled by Philip the Fair in
1305.
He returned later and then moved on to
Cologne where he died in 1308.
>> Scottus' proof to ex for the existence
of God um is not unrelated to the kinds
of proof that you find in Aquinas. So
for example, Scottus thinks that you can
formulate an argument for a first cause
and that you can formulate an argument
for a final goal of all existence and he
also thinks that you can formulate an
argument for a most perfect of all
beings. He takes much more trouble than
Aquinus to try to show that this is one
and the same being uh and that you
shouldn't really call it God until
you've managed to show it. It's got
certain attributes. But Scottus thinks
that the kinds of proof that we find in
Aquinas aren't in themselves
sufficiently rigorous.
What he objects to is the fact that
Aquinus's premises are contingent. That
is to say, they're not premises that are
logically necessary. But for a good
Arisotilian argument, Scottus thinks you
need premises that are logically
necessary such that they couldn't be
false.
So he replaces the first premise of the
cosmological argument, for example, with
the claim that it's possible that there
are caused beings, which he thinks is
necessarily true. From this he infers
very quickly that it's possible that
there are causes and rejecting the
infinite regress that it's possible that
there is a first cause. Then he makes a
move rather similar to ansomes
ontological argument. Uh he reasons that
if God exists at all his existence is
logically necessary. This means that
either God's existence is necessary or
it's impossible. But he's already shown
that the existence of a first cause is
possible which quite validly yields the
conclusion that God's existence is
necessary and hence that God exists.
Scottus drove the first wedge between
theology and philosophy.
He believed that terms such as being,
one, true, and good had only one
meaning. Without this, knowledge of God
would be impossible.
In 1543, Capernacus put forward his
theory that the Earth rotated around the
sun, a notion taken up by Galileo.
Humankind's perception of the universe
would never be the same again.
>> [music]